Jeffrey Auriemma

Software Engineer && Manager

Hershey, Pennsylvania

https://jdauriemma.com 🔀 jeff@auriemma.xyz

bignimbus

My colleagues would describe me as outgoing, personable and passionate about great software and frictionless user experiences. Developing software is hard and expensive, but conversation is easy and cheap. In the planning process, I try to be a part of the conversation early to get a handle on the business case for the feature. This helps my team deliver software that has the highest impact at the lowest cost possible. As a former teacher and musician, I know how important communication and creativity are to the success of the group. This has been a key influence on my style as a manager, mentor, and contributor to a variety of projects across a variety of systems during my career.

SKILLS

Leadership	UI development	Server development	Web platform
public speaking teaching	javascript typescript	node.js ruby rails rspec	accessibility
onboarding	html 5 css + preprocessors	postgresql graphql	internationalization
removing hiring bias	react web audio api	socket.io webrtc webpack	dev tools responsive design
software fundamentals	media streams jest	babel	performance optimization
agile performance rubrics	angular.js jquery		browser compatibility
tdd one-on-ones	css/svg/smil animations		
technical writing			

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer at Handshake

August 2019 - Current

- Design and document Ruby and TypeScript architecture for text translations and date/time formatting to support international expansion on a fixed timeline
- Work with marketing and product stakeholders to implement an MVP referral program through a vendor, driving direct-toconsumer cost per acquisition downward
- Support transition from Enzyme to React Testing Library by helping to give a component unit testing workshop for colleagues
- Give talks on product and general software engineering topics for engineering, design, and product peers

Senior Engineer && Manager at Visibly (formerly Opternative)

January 2019 - August 2019

- Manage software engineer evaluations, compensation packages, and professional development for a small team while making daily contributions to production code
- Responsible for technical implementation of projects: empower direct reports to take on user stories with autonomy that play to their strengths and foster new skills where possible, make key technical contributions where appropriate, and meet key timelines in close coordination with stakeholders
- Overhaul software engineering recruitment and interview process
- Work closely with product owners, designers, and project managers to identify key decision-making criteria, including longterm app architecture implications, precise estimates, and domain knowledge-related nuances
- Lead biweekly sprint retrospective for all engineering and product personnel focusing on continuous improvement of process and product
- Completed courses for ISO 13485:2016, FDA QSRs, and EU MDD

Senior Software Engineer at Visibly (formerly Opternative)

January 2018 - January 2019

- Key contributor and innovator to the development of "Single Device Over Refraction," the first-ever application of pure HTML5 technology to create a 100% voice user interface on the web available to the public
- Create, evangelize, and mantain modern front-end architecture for various production features and applications
- Rapidly prototype cutting-edge user interfaces early in a product's lifecycle to ensure designers and other stakeholders can agree on a consistent vision that takes full advantage of the web browser's capabilities
- Advise other engineers on database schema and data modeling best practices
- Contribute to candidate interviews, colleague evaluations, and personnel decision-making

- Overhaul team metrics gathering by collecting and gathering qualitative and quantitative information pertaining to the software engineering process
- Mentor and teach teammates through one-on-one sessions and group lunch-and-learns on a variety of software development best practices, with an emphasis on front-end development techniques
- Contribute patches to under-maintained open-source projects to drive company initiatives forward without having to reinvent the wheel (and improving company visibility to the developer community)
- Drive revenue by mining production data and third-party analytics services to identify opportunities and implement solutions to improve outcomes for users
- Facilitate international expansion by coordinating technical management of static assets and translation dictionaries for English, Spanish, and German
- Contribute and sign off on comprehensive technical documentation for the FDA de novo medical device application process

Software Engineer at Visibly (formerly Opternative)

August 2015 - January 2018

- Pushed and empowered teammates to incorporate principles in the Agile Manifesto in different aspects of the software development lifecycle
- Proactively improved low-level code quality and consistency by implementing git hooks, linters, and documentation for Ruby, JavaScript, and CSS/Sass/SCSS
- As the first remote-only employee, established a model for effective off-site collaboration within the engineering team and throughout the rest of the company
- Designed, developed, and deployed the first iteration of the company's Engineering Blog (currently offline, version 2 coming soon)
- Audited entire marketing site for accessibility issues, reported findings to the team, created user stories for actionable items, and executed those items to ensure compliance and broad usability
- Quarterbacked transition from Angular 1.2 + Sprokets to React + Babel + Webpack and other modern UI development best practices
- Planned and taught a biweekly "learn to code" course for non-engineering colleagues
- Generate technical specifications, detailed implementation plans, user stories, and estimates for large units of work
- Created the company's first live style guide to facilitate higher-quality design-developer interactions, code reuse, and UI consistency

Junior Front End Developer at Discovery Education

July 2014 - July 2015

https://discoveryeducation.com

- Developed prototype and production code for a distributed, infographic-heavy data visualization feature
- Conceived, built, and deployed a "Styleguide as a Service" for bootstrapping new applications and rapid prototyping with a small team of designers and developers
- Develop and maintain features and unit tests in a variety of education webapps using Backbone, Marionette, and ColdFusion
- Improved software development speeds by identifying areas of high technical debt and refactoring those to comply with team norms and best practices

Music Teacher; Arts Liaison at Chicago Public Schools

August 2012 - June 2014

Music Teacher at South Brunswick Public Schools

August 2008 - June 2012

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Music at The College of New Jersey (Ewing, NJ) **2004 - 2008**

music education magna cum laude